<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xml/base.min.xml" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>./</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="./index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>./en/post/</link>
      <guid>./en/post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ppsn-2024httpppsn2024fh-ooeat-workshop-30-years-of-edas&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ppsn2024.fh-ooe.at&#34;&gt;PPSN 2024&lt;/a&gt; Workshop: 30 Years of EDAs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimation of Distribution Algorithms (EDAs) have been an active and
impactful research area now for around thirty years. The publication of
Population Based Incremental Learning (PBIL) in 1994, crystallised
research focused around estimating and sampling models of the
distribution of value in a solution space as an operating mechanism for
population-based metaheuristic search. Over the last 30 years, EDAs have
developed from building univariate (fully-factorised) probabilistic
models on simple theoretical problems (OneMax, Trapk, etc) to pervasive
application across most problem representation spaces, solving
challenging benchmark datasets, demonstrating competitive performance on
single- and multi-objective and dynamic problems and used on induction
of machine learning models to address supervised learning, feature
selection, clustering and reinforcement learning problems as well as on
a wide range of real world applications including bioinformatics,
biomedicine, computational neuroscience, industry 4.0, evolvable
hardware design and quantum computing. Journals like Evolutionary
Computation, IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation or
International Journal of Approximate Reasoning have organised special
issues on EDAs. Conferences have shown an interest in hosting tutorials
on EDAs, since the first seminal one at PPSN VI in 2000 to the recent
presentation related to theory at this PPSN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently EDAs have become a focus of interest for foundational
theoretical research on population-based metaheuristics. The explicit
mathematical nature of the EDA update mechanism lends itself to
theoretical examination using the established tools of run time analysis
as well as EDA-specific analysis methods. This led to several deep
insights on the working principles of EDAs, e.g., why they cope well
with noise, how they leave local optima faster than traditional
evolutionary algorithms, and how the parameters lead to the undesirable
effect of genetic drift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this workshop is to mark the thirty year milestone in a
mature and diverse topic of continuing interest and to encourage
thinking on key open questions and future directions. We invite
participants to contribute short talks aimed at stimulating discussion
and possible collaboration. Topics may include but are not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Novel probabilistic models for EDAs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features make a suitable application for EDAs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hybrid probabilistic models for EDAs on mixed variable
representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What mathematical tools will advance theoretical study of EDAs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can theoretical study of EDAs inform the broader EA theory?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;target-participants-and-audience&#34;&gt;Target Participants and Audience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek participation from researchers and users of EDAs from the
population-based metaheuristics community as well as those interested in
deepening the theoretical analysis of this algorithm class.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
