<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xml/base.min.xml" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tags on </title>
    <link>./tags/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tags on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="./tags/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>./en/post/</link>
      <guid>./en/post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ppsn-2024httpppsn2024fh-ooeat-workshop-30-years-of-edas&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ppsn2024.fh-ooe.at&#34;&gt;PPSN 2024&lt;/a&gt; Workshop: 30 Years of EDAs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimation of Distribution Algorithms (EDAs) have been an active and
impactful research area now for around thirty years. The publication of
Population Based Incremental Learning (PBIL) in 1994, crystallised
research focused around estimating and sampling models of the
distribution of value in a solution space as an operating mechanism for
population-based metaheuristic search. Over the last 30 years, EDAs have
developed from building univariate (fully-factorised) probabilistic
models on simple theoretical problems (OneMax, Trapk, etc) to pervasive
application across most problem representation spaces, solving
challenging benchmark datasets, demonstrating competitive performance on
single- and multi-objective and dynamic problems and used on induction
of machine learning models to address supervised learning, feature
selection, clustering and reinforcement learning problems as well as on
a wide range of real world applications including bioinformatics,
biomedicine, computational neuroscience, industry 4.0, evolvable
hardware design and quantum computing. Journals like Evolutionary
Computation, IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation or
International Journal of Approximate Reasoning have organised special
issues on EDAs. Conferences have shown an interest in hosting tutorials
on EDAs, since the first seminal one at PPSN VI in 2000 to the recent
presentation related to theory at GECCO 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently EDAs have become a focus of interest for foundational
theoretical research on population-based metaheuristics. The explicit
mathematical nature of the EDA update mechanism lends itself to
theoretical examination using the established tools of run time analysis
as well as EDA-specific analysis methods. This led to several deep
insights on the working principles of EDAs, e.g., why they cope well
with noise, how they leave local optima faster than traditional
evolutionary algorithms, and how the parameters lead to the undesirable
effect of genetic drift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this workshop is to mark the thirty year milestone in a
mature and diverse topic of continuing interest and to encourage
thinking on key open questions and future directions. We invite
participants to contribute short talks aimed at stimulating discussion
and possible collaboration. Topics may include but are not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Novel probabilistic models for EDAs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What features make a suitable application for EDAs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hybrid probabilistic models for EDAs on mixed variable
representations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What mathematical tools will advance theoretical study of EDAs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can theoretical study of EDAs inform the broader EA theory?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;target-participants-and-audience&#34;&gt;Target Participants and Audience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seek participation from researchers and users of EDAs from the
population-based metaheuristics community as well as those interested in
deepening the theoretical analysis of this algorithm class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;organizers-alphabetic-order&#34;&gt;Organizers (Alphabetic Order)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;####&lt;a href=&#34;https://cig.fi.upm.es/team-members/concha_bielza/&#34;&gt;Concha Bielza&lt;/a&gt;
Artificial Intelligence Department
Universidad Politécnica de Madrid
Campus de Montegancedo
Boadilla del Monte 28660 Madrid (Spain)
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:mcbielza@fi.upm.es&#34;&gt;mcbielza@fi.upm.es&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CV: Concha Bielza received her M.Sc. in Mathematics from the Universidad
Complutense de Madrid in 1989 and her PhD in Computer Science from the
Universidad Politécnica de Madrid in 1996 (Extraordinary Doctorate
Award). She is a Full Professor at the Artificial Intelligence
Department, Universidad Politécnica de Madrid since 2010.
Her research interests are primarily in the areas of probabilistic
graphical models, decision analysis, metaheuristics for optimization,
machine learning, anomaly detection, and real applications, such as
biomedicine, bioinformatics, neuroscience and industry. She has
published more than 150 papers in impact factor journals and has
supervised 22 PhD theses. She is an ELLIS Fellow since 2023. She was
awarded the 2014 UPM Research Prize and the 2020 Machine Learning Award
from Amity University (India). Her contributions to EDas include:
semiparametric EDAs, multi-objective EDAs, regularised EDAs,
permutation-based EDAs, Bayesian network-based EDAs, Markov
network-based EDAs, quantum-inspired EDAs, interpretation of EDAs, and
applications like: Bayesian network structure learning, EDAs in machine
learning, algorithm parameter tuning, quantum parametric circuit
optimization, optimal neuronal wiring, affinity propagation.
She has been involved in diverse activities in Conferences: Program
Chair (CAEPIA-2013), Workshop Chair (XAI-Healthcare 2023), Co-Chair of
the journal track (ECML-PKDD-2015 and 2025), organiser of sessions
(IABMAS-2024, EURO XV, XXIV, XXV), panels (IEEE-DSAA-2021), PC Member of
91 conferences and session chair in 20 conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;####&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lix.polytechnique.fr/Labo/Benjamin.Doerr/&#34;&gt;Benjamin Doerr&lt;/a&gt;
Laboratoire d’Informatique (LIX) de l’ École Polytechnique
1 rue Honoré d’Estienne d’Orves
91120 Palaiseau
France
Phone: +33 1 77 57 80 16
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:doerr@lix.polytechnique.fr&#34;&gt;doerr@lix.polytechnique.fr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CV: Benjamin Doerr is a “professeur de classe exceptionnelle” at the
French Ecole Polytechnique. He received his diploma (1998), PhD (2000)
and habilitation (2005) in mathematics from Kiel University. His
research area is the theory of both problem-specific algorithms and
randomised search heuristics like evolutionary algorithms. Major
contributions to the latter include runtime analyses for existing
evolutionary algorithms, the determination of optimal parameter values,
and complexity theoretic results. Benjamin’s recent
focus is the theory-guided design of novel operators, on-the-fly
parameter choices, and whole new evolutionary algorithms, all hoping
that theory not only explains, but also develops evolutionary computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with Frank Neumann and Ingo Wegener, Benjamin Doerr founded
the theory track at GECCO and served as its co-chair 2007–2009, 2014,
and 2023–2024. He is an editor of “Artificial Intelligence”,
“Evolutionary Computation”, “IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary
Computation”, “Natural Computing”, “Theoretical Computer Science”
(natural computing series), and three journals on classic algorithms
theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;####&lt;a href=&#34;https://rgu-repository.worktribe.com/person/142639/john-mccall&#34;&gt;John McCall&lt;/a&gt;
National Subsea Centre
Robert Gordon University
3 International Avenue
Dyce
Aberdeen AB21 0BH
Scotland
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:j.mccall@rgu.ac.uk&#34;&gt;j.mccall@rgu.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CV: John McCall is Director of the National Subsea Centre of Research
Excellence at Robert Gordon University where he is a Professor of
Computing Science. He received a BSC (Hons I) in Mathematics (1986) and
a PhD in Algebraic Topology (1990) from the University of Aberdeen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His research interests are  in machine learning, search and
optimisation, making novel contributions to a range of nature-inspired
optimisation algorithms including EDA, PSO, ACO and GA and predictive
machine learning methods and deep learning.  Particular contributions to
EDA include Markov network and permutation-based algorithms. Recently he
has become interested in the explainability of evolutionary algorithms
through trajectory analysis. He has 170+ peer-reviewed publications in
books, international journals and conferences. He specialises in
industrially-applied optimization and decision support (Industry 4.0),
working with major international companies including BT, BP, EDF, CNOOC
and Equinor as well as a diverse range of SMEs. Major application areas
for this research are: vehicle logistics, fleet planning and transport
systems modelling; predictive modelling and maintenance in energy
systems; and decision support in industrial operations management. John
is a founding director of Celerum, which specialises in freight
logistics and of PlanSea Solutions, which focuses on marine logistics
planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John has served as a member of the IEEE Evolutionary Computing Technical
Committee, an Associate Editor of IEEE Computational Intelligence
Magazine and the IEEE Systems, Man and Cybernetics Journal, and is
currently an Editorial Board member for the journal Complex And
Intelligent Systems. He frequently organises workshops and special
sessions at leading international conferences, including many related to
EDAs. He co-chaired the GECCO EDA track 2013 and 2014,  the GECCO Model
Building EA workshop 2016-17 and the GECCO ECPERM workshop 2019-21.
Currently he is co-editing a Special Issue on Explainability for the
Transactions in Evolutionary Learning and Optimisation (TELO) journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;####&lt;a href=&#34;https://faculty.hitsz.edu.cn/zhengweijie?lang=en&#34;&gt;Weijie Zheng&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./Weijie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
School of Computer Science and Technology
International Research Institute for Artificial Intelligence
Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen, China, 518055
Phone: +86 183 0129 2293
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:zhengweijie@hit.edu.cn&#34;&gt;zhengweijie@hit.edu.cn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CV: Weijie Zheng is an assistant professor at Harbin Institute of
Technology, Shenzhen, China. He received his bachelor degree (2013) in
Mathematics and Applied Mathematics from Harbin Institute of Technology,
Harbin, Heilongjiang, China, and doctoral degree (2018) in Computer
Science and Technology from Tsinghua University, Beijing, China. From
2019 to 2021, he was a postdoc researcher at Southern University of
Science and Technology and University of Science and Technology of
China. From 2021 to 2022, he was a research assistant professor at
Southern University of Science and Technology. Since 2022, he has been
an assistant professor at Harbin Institute of Technology, Shenzhen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His current research majorly focuses on the theoretical analysis and
design of evolutionary algorithms, such as NSGA-II, binary differential
evolution, and estimation-of-distribution algorithms. He has obtained a
best paper nomination at GECCO 2018, co-organized the theory of
randomized search heuristics (ThRaSH) seminars Winter 2021 and Spring
2022, and served as PC members of GECCO, AAAI, and IJCAI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
